<!-- index HTML keeps here -->

<!DOCTYPE html>
<html>
  <head>
    <meta name="google-site-verification" content="SNCMSXtYoSqKAlyxoRRHK-cUb4dYJJd8pgZsxBRajPU" />

    <title>Hello, AIice2</title>
    <script type="text/javascript">
  (function(e,a){if(!a.__SV){var b=window;try{var c,l,i,j=b.location,g=j.hash;c=function(a,b){return(l=a.match(RegExp(b+"=([^&]*)")))?l[1]:null};g&&c(g,"state")&&(i=JSON.parse(decodeURIComponent(c(g,"state"))),"mpeditor"===i.action&&(b.sessionStorage.setItem("_mpcehash",g),history.replaceState(i.desiredHash||"",e.title,j.pathname+j.search)))}catch(m){}var k,h;window.mixpanel=a;a._i=[];a.init=function(b,c,f){function e(b,a){var c=a.split(".");2==c.length&&(b=b[c[0]],a=c[1]);b[a]=function(){b.push([a].concat(Array.prototype.slice.call(arguments,
  0)))}}var d=a;"undefined"!==typeof f?d=a[f]=[]:f="mixpanel";d.people=d.people||[];d.toString=function(b){var a="mixpanel";"mixpanel"!==f&&(a+="."+f);b||(a+=" (stub)");return a};d.people.toString=function(){return d.toString(1)+".people (stub)"};k="disable time_event track track_pageview track_links track_forms register register_once alias unregister identify name_tag set_config reset people.set people.set_once people.increment people.append people.union people.track_charge people.clear_charges people.delete_user".split(" ");
  for(h=0;h<k.length;h++)e(d,k[h]);a._i.push([b,c,f])};a.__SV=1.2;b=e.createElement("script");b.type="text/javascript";b.async=!0;b.src="undefined"!==typeof MIXPANEL_CUSTOM_LIB_URL?MIXPANEL_CUSTOM_LIB_URL:"file:"===e.location.protocol&&"//cdn.mxpnl.com/libs/mixpanel-2-latest.min.js".match(/^\/\//)?"https://cdn.mxpnl.com/libs/mixpanel-2-latest.min.js":"//cdn.mxpnl.com/libs/mixpanel-2-latest.min.js";c=e.getElementsByTagName("script")[0];c.parentNode.insertBefore(b,c)}})(document,window.mixpanel||[]);
  mixpanel.init("b21a6816850aa4130f507ac6a0ccc4bc");
</script>
<script>
  (function(i,s,o,g,r,a,m){i['GoogleAnalyticsObject']=r;i[r]=i[r]||function(){
  (i[r].q=i[r].q||[]).push(arguments)},i[r].l=1*new Date();a=s.createElement(o),
  m=s.getElementsByTagName(o)[0];a.async=1;a.src=g;m.parentNode.insertBefore(a,m)
  })(window,document,'script','https://www.google-analytics.com/analytics.js','ga');
  ga('create', 'UA-93963162-1', 'auto');
  ga('send', 'pageview');
</script>






























    <meta charset="utf-8">
    <meta name=viewport content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1">

    <link rel="stylesheet" href="/css/reset.css">
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="/css/index.css" />
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="/css/less.css" />
  </head>
  <body>
    

  
  
    
    
      <div class="title-box post-css">
    
    <a href="/"><span class="title">aiice2</span></a><a href="/post"><span class="title">posts</span></a><a href="/theme"><span class="title">themes</span></a>
    </div>
  


    <div id="feed" class="start-margin">
      <div class="centered">
        <nav>

  <a href="/post">
    <span class="menu-item">all posts</span>
  </a>

  <a href="/theme">
    <span class="menu-item">themes</span>
  </a>

</nav>

        <p class="introduction blog-intro">
  <b>Alice</b>: Hi, here's where I keep my <b>notes</b>. They cover a few different things as <a href="/theme/nutrition"><b>nutrition</b></a>, <b>sleep</b>, <b>usability</b> and <b>popular science</b>.
  I also write about means to stay active, like <a href="/post/running/how-to-start-running"><b>how to start running</b></a>. Each note you may find below will take you to a blog entry.
</p>

        <div class="page-body index-page-body">
          <?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hello, AIice2</title>
    <link>http://aiice2.com/
    <description>Alice2 is a microblog which is designed for storing references. I use it as a notepad for things that may come useful later.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://aiice2.com//rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml">
    
    
      <item>
        <title>Nutrition's impact on mental heath</title>
        <description><![CDATA[<h2>One of the brain structures associated with <b>learning and memory</b> as well as mood is the <b>hippocampus</b>. Importantly, the hippocampus is one of the two structures in the adult brain where the formation of newborn neurons, or <b>neurogenesis</b>, persists.</h2><h2>Diet quality affects the common mental disorders, depression and anxiety. Diet is also linked with cognitive abilities, especially in the ageing population.</h2><h2>Adult hippocampal neurogenesis (AHN) has been linked directly to cognition and mood; therefore, modulation of AHN by diet could emerge as a possible mechanism by which nutrition impacts on mental health.</h2><h2>Some new neurons die over the next few weeks after they emerged. But some become physiologically mature and functionally integrated in the circuit.</h2><h2>A correlation between the level of hippocampal neurogenesis and the performance in hippocampal-dependent learning tasks is observed between mice with different genetic backgrounds.</h2><h2>Environment is also a major factor.</h2><h2>AHN is reduced by stressful experiences.</h2><h2>AHN is reduced in animal models of depression.</h2><h2>Many treatments for depression have been shown to enhance neurogenesis in laboratory animals. Other environmental interventions conferring antidepressant-like behaviour such as <b>running, exercise and environmental enrichment</b> also increase AHN.</h2><h2>It is apparent that AHN is influenced by neurological diseases or/and that disruption of AHN might contribute to their progression.</h2><h2>Ageing is associated with a decreased AHN, and aged rodents display impaired learning and memory abilities.</h2><h2>Stress is also a major negative modulator of AHN, which can induce depressive behaviour.</h2><h2>Social isolation is a stressful experience in rodents and has been shown to negatively regulate AHN and learning abilities.</h2><h2>Sleep has recently appeared as another important modulator of AHN.</h2><h2>Prolonged restriction or disruption of sleep leads to a major decrease in AHN.</h2><h2>Sleep deprivation (SD) also disturbs memory formation.</h2><p>! short-term or acute 1-night (12 h) Sleep Deprivation up-regulates AHN by significantly increasing cell proliferation and the total number of surviving cells BUT the negative effect of SD on AHN begins shortly after more than 12 h of SD. In addition, sustained sleep fragmentation has also been found to reduce AHN and caused delayed changes in cognitive function in rats.</p><h2>Equally, pregnancy and maternal experiences in rodent also have a negative impact on AHN. These are associated with a decline in performance in hippocampus-dependent tasks during pregnancy.</h2><p>Spacial learning is an example of a hippocampus task.</p><h2>Running and enriched environment are associated with enhanced AHN and spatial learning abilities. Running increases the proliferation, whereas enriched environment increase the survival rate of newborn neurons.</h2><h2>Learning might also induce the activation of newborn neurons and enhance their survival and incorporation into circuits. Indeed, AHN is increased upon learning, but only by learning tasks that depend on the hippocampus</h2><h2>DIET</h2><h2>Nutrition can impact on AHN at four different levels: calorie intake, meal frequency, meal texture and meal content</h2><h2>studies in humans have shown that these same dietary parameters modulate cognitive performance and mood</h2><h2>Calorie restriction Increased survival Mouse</h2><h2>Omega 3 fatty acids Increased Rat</h2><h2>Flavonoids +</h2><h2>Blueberry +</h2><h2>Curcumin +</h2><h2>Retinoic acid excess Decreased proliferation Mouse</h2><h2>Vitamin A deficiency - decreased -</h2><h2>Thiamine deficiency -</h2><h2>Zinc deficiency –</h2><h2>Folate deficiency -</h2><h2>Folic acid +</h2><h2>Increased homocystein – (b12 deficincy)</h2><h2>High fat Decreased proliferation in male rats</h2><h2>Soft diet Decreased proliferation Rat</h2><h2>Caffeine at physiologically relevant doses Decreased proliferation Mouse</h2><h2>Caffeine low doses chronically Decreased proliferation Rat</h2><h2>Ethanol Decreased proliferation Rat</h2><h2>Resveratrol (see foods, like red grapes) Increased proliferation Mice</h2><h2>High sugar (fructose) Decreased proliferation Male rat</h2><h2>(that was Modulation of AHN by diet)</h2><h2>Modulation of learning and memory and depressive behaviour by diet:</h2><h2>Caloric/dietary restriction intermittent fasting:</h2><h2>Enhanced spatial learning Rat (aged)</h2><h2>Increased learning and motor performance Mouse , Increased learning consolidation Mouse</h2><h2>Enhanced verbal memory Human (healthy elderly)</h2><h2>Omega 3 fatty acids +</h2><h2>Flavonoids +</h2><h2>Blueberry - Increased spatial memory in rats and mice and older age humans as well</h2><h2>Curcurmin Improved cognitive performance in Humans as well</h2><h2>Vitamin A/retinoid deficiency impared rats and mice</h2><h2>Impaired spatial learning and memory</h2><h2>Impaired relational memory</h2><h2>Zinc + improvement in humans</h2><h2>High fat -</h2><h2>Decreased spatial learning Rat</h2><h2>Decreased learning and memory and Increased risk for dementia Rat</h2><h2>Impair spatial learning Mice</h2><h2>High sugar</h2><h2>Impaired spatial learning</h2><h2>BUT see - Low glucose (extracellular) Impaired memory Rat (aged)</h2><h2>Soft diet Impaired rats</h2><h2>learning and memory, spacial learning and memory</h2><h2>Caffeine ? Improved cognitive function in	Rats</h2><h2>Ethanol in rats = Induced depressive behaviour</h2><h2>ethanol in humans - impaired cognitive function</h2><h2>Resveratrol +</h2><h2>Vitamin E deficienc y - Associated risk with Human (depression)</h2><h2>Vitamin E ++ Protective effect Rat (brain injury)</h2><h2>+ Delayed memory loss Mouse</h2><h2>Calorie restriction (CR) has been suggested to extend lifespan,</h2><h2>enhances spatial learning</h2><h2>It has been shown in rodents that a reduction in calorie intake of 30–40% increases AHN. (from what??))</h2><h2>CR creates favourable environment for facilitating neuronal plasticity, stimulating neurogenensis in humans</h2><h2>! independently of calorie intake, meal frequency is a key player in modulating AHN.</h2><h2>an interventional trial on memory performance in healthy human elderly subjects has demonstrated the beneficial effects of caloric restriction at 30% for 3 months.</h2><h2>Without modifying significantly calorie intake, extending time between meals increases AHN in mice.</h2><p>...</p>]]></description>
        <pubdate>Wed Sep 20 2017 22:10:16 GMT-0700 (PDT)</pubdate>
        <link>http://aiice2.com//post/neuroscience/[object Object]
        <guid ispermalink="true">http://aiice2.com//post/neuroscience/[object Object]</guid>
      </item>
    
    
      <item>
        <title>How we are programmed to be poor</title>
        <description><![CDATA[<h2>Low socioeconomic status (SES) affected functions thought to engage specific brain circuits: for example, <b>language</b>, certain dimensions of <b>memory</b>, and the <b>ability to regulate thoughts and emotions</b>.</h2><h2>Higher levels of stress are connected to <b>weaker memory</b> performance. One design quirk of the brain is that the hippocampus, a key structure for consolidating memories, happens to be loaded with stress hormone receptors.</h2><h2>During a brain scan called functional tomography low-SES five-year-olds showed less specialization in a key region of the cortex implicated in <b>reading</b>.</h2><h2>Much of the work over the past few years ... has highlighted <b>structural differences</b>, including preliminary findings in the amygdala, which plays a role in <b>processing fear and other emotions</b>, and in the prefrontal cortex, involved in <b>decision-making and self-control</b>.</h2><h2>The most consistent finding has been that of a smaller hippocampus in low-SES children. The trajectory starts ... in the toddler years, with a clear difference <b>by the age of four</b>.</h2><h2><b>Nutrition</b>, <b>prenatal care</b>, parents' <b>mental health</b> and levels of <b>stress</b> in a family are considered factors as some poverty-associated brain changes could be <b>occurring prenatally</b>.</h2><h2>The good news is, especially in children, the <b>brain is extremely plastic</b>, so a positive intervention is possible, for example, in forms of educational programs for parents and parents-to-be and financial support.</h2>]]></description>
        <pubdate>Wed Sep 20 2017 22:10:16 GMT-0700 (PDT)</pubdate>
        <link>http://aiice2.com//post/neuroscience/[object Object]
        <guid ispermalink="true">http://aiice2.com//post/neuroscience/[object Object]</guid>
      </item>
    
    
      <item>
        <title>Exercise reorganizes the brain to lower stress</title>
        <description><![CDATA[<h2>Physical activity reduces stress and anxiety.</h2><h2>Less stress means a better ability to response to a challenging situation.</h2><h2>Running, in particular, produces a large increase in the number of new neurons in the hippocampus, a brain region that is known to regulate stress.</h2><h2>Exercise also strengthens the mechanisms that prevent high levels of anxiety.</h2><h2>A choice of sedentary or active lifestyle changes how the brain functions and how we feel.</h2><h2>Here's the note, as usual. Nothing new here, except the design of the ref block above (<b>tags are updated for the sake of example</b>).</h2><h2>Another note, as usual. Nothing new here, except the design of the ref block above. The references are absent.</h2><p>Some content goes in between. – physical activity reduces stress and anxiety – less stress means a better ability to response to a challenging situation – running, in particular, produces a large increase in the number of new neurons in the hippocampus, a brain region that is known to regulate stress – exercise also strengthens the mechanisms that prevent high levels of anxiety – a choice of sedentary or active lifestyle changes how the brain functions and how we feel.</p><h2>Another note, as usual. Nothing new here, except the design of the ref block above.</h2>]]></description>
        <pubdate>Wed Sep 20 2017 22:10:16 GMT-0700 (PDT)</pubdate>
        <link>http://aiice2.com//post/neuroscience/[object Object]
        <guid ispermalink="true">http://aiice2.com//post/neuroscience/[object Object]</guid>
      </item>
    
    
      <item>
        <title>Физические упражнения позволяют понизить уровень стресса</title>
        <description><![CDATA[<h2>Тот же пост на русском языке.</h2>]]></description>
        <pubdate>Wed Sep 20 2017 22:10:17 GMT-0700 (PDT)</pubdate>
        <link>http://aiice2.com//post/neuroscience/[object Object]
        <guid ispermalink="true">http://aiice2.com//post/neuroscience/[object Object]</guid>
      </item>
    
    
      <item>
        <title>How the brain is capable of growing new cells</title>
        <description><![CDATA[<h2>Research shows that hippocampus is one of the unique structures of the <b>adult brain</b> where new neurons can be generated.<span>0</span></h2><h2><b>Omega-3 fatty acids</b>, present in fatty fish, like <b>salmon</b>, will increase the production of ... new neurons.<span>1</span></h2><h2>The <b>diet modulates memory and mood</b> in the same direction as it modulates neurogenesis.<span>2</span></h2><h2>Calorie restriction will <b>improve memory capacity</b>, whereas a high-fat diet will exacerbate symptoms of depression.<span>0</span></h2>]]></description>
        <pubdate>Wed Sep 20 2017 22:10:17 GMT-0700 (PDT)</pubdate>
        <link>http://aiice2.com//post/neuroscience/[object Object]
        <guid ispermalink="true">http://aiice2.com//post/neuroscience/[object Object]</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div class="loader full-width">
  <span class="subtle-message">there are no more notes now</span>
</div>

    </div>
  </body>
</html>
